### **CONTACT INFORMATION**

The Biodesign Institute Phone +1 (702) 907-8272
Arizona State University Email tfursten@asu.edu
PO Box 875301 Website http://tfursten.github.io

Tempe, Arizona 85287-5301

#### **CURRENT RESEARCH**

I am a computational biologist interested in studying evolution and population genetics in a spatial context. Most of my research focuses on consequences of isolation-by-distance, a phenomenon which results in the formation of spatial genetic structure in a population due to limited dispersal. I have developed several spatially-explicit individual based simulations to better understand how isolation-by-distance is affected by different dispersal distributions and different mating types. I am also working on developing a Bayesian method for estimating neighborhood size which roughly quantifies the spatial-genetic structure in a population due to isolation-by-distance.

## **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. Molecular and Cellular Biology Arizona State University Exp. 2016

Advisor: Reed Cartwright

B.S. Bioinformatics and Genomics Arizona State University 2010

magna cum laude

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Furstenau, TN**, and RA Cartwright (2015). The effect of the dispersal kernel on isolation-by-distance in a continuous population. Manuscript submitted for publication. http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.01085

Pizzio GA, Paez-Valencia J, Khadilkar AS, Regmi K, Patron-Soberano A, Zhang S, Sanchez-Lares J, **Furstenau T**, Li J, Sanchez-Gomez C, Valencia-Mayoral P, Yadav UP, Ayre BG and RA Gaxiola (2015). *Arabidopsis* proton-pumping pyrophosphatase *AVP1* expresses strongly in phloem where it is required for PPi metabolism and photosynthate partitioning. *Plant Physiology* **167**:1541-1553. doi:10.1104/pp.114.254342

### **PRESENTATIONS**

# **Talks**

Bayesian estimation of neighborhood size using composite marginal likelihoods 2015 Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution · Vienna, Austria 2015 Bayesian estimation of neighborhood size using composite marginal likelihoods Molecular and Cellular Biology Colloquium · The Biodesign Institute Evolution of Self-Incompatibility: Investigating the role of self-incompatibility systems in 2014 the prevention of biparental inbreeding. Molecular and Cellular Biology Colloquium · The Biodesign Institute Evolution of Self-Incompatibility: Investigating the role of self-incompatibility systems in 2013 the prevention of biparental inbreeding Molecular and Cellular Biology Colloquium · Arizona State University *Is the*  $H^+$ -pyrophosphatase involved in the regulation of sucrose transport in plants? 2012

Molecular and Cellular Biology Colloquium · Arizona State University

#### **Posters and Abstracts**

2014	The effect of the dispersal distribution on isolation-by-distance in a continuous population
	Society for the Study of Evolution · Raleigh, NC
2014	Characterization of Transgenic Arabidopsis thaliana overexpressing AVP1 and PLAFP
	Undergraduate Research Poster Symposium · Arizona State University · Tempe, AZ
	Presented by Sean Wilson (undergraduate mentee)
2012	H <sup>+</sup> -PPase AVP1 is necessary for phloem development in Arabidopsis thaliana
	Molecular and Cellular Biology Graduate Student Retreat · Tempe, AZ
2012	H <sup>+</sup> -PPase AVP1 is necessary for phloem development in Arabidopsis thaliana

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2013-Present	Graduate Student with Reed Cartwright
	Center for Human and Comparative Genomics
	The Biodesign Institute
	Arizona State University · Tempe, AZ
2010-2013	Research Assistant with Roberto Gaxiola
	School of Life Science
	Arizona State University · Tempe, AZ
2009-2010	Undergraduate Student Researcher with Lei Lei
	School of Life Science
	Arizona State University · Tempe, AZ

American Society of Plant Biologists · Austin, TX

#### **AWARDS**

2015	ASU	Graduate Education Travel Award
2015	ASU	School of Life Sciences Travel Award

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# **Arizona State University**

(	Courses:		
	2014	General Genetics	Head TA
	2014	Introduction to Computational Molecular Biology	Innovative TA
	2013	Concepts in Plant Biology iCourse	Instructor
	2011-2015	General Genetics	Teaching Associate
	2011	General Biology I & 2 Laboratory	Teaching Associate
	2010	Genetic Engineering and Society Laboratory	Teaching Associate

# Undergraduate Mentorship:

2011-2013 Honors Thesis Mentor · Sean Wilson

Wilson S, Furstenau T, and R Gaxiola. Characterization of Transgenic *Arabidopsis thaliana* Overexpressing a Type I H<sup>+</sup> Pyrophosphatase and the Phloem Lipid-Associated Family Protein. http://hdl.handle.net/2286/R.I.23607

## SERVICE AND OUTREACH

2015	Molecular and Cellular Biology and Microbiology Retreat Poster Judge
2015	Software Carpentry Workshop Helper
2015	Night of the Open Door Volunteer
2010-present	Ask-A-Biologist Volunteer Corespondent
2011-2013	Green Labs Initiative Coordinator and Promoter
2012-2013	Phosphorus Sustainability Research Coordination Network Core Participant
2011-2012	Obama Scholars Mentor

## **SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS**

Society for the Study of Evolution Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution Graduate Integrative Society for Environmental Interdisciplinary Research Central Arizona Chapter of the Association for Women in Science

#### PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

2013	Next Generation Population Genomics for Non-model Taxa Workshop
	American Genetics Association · Cornell University · Ithica, NY
2011	Univector Plasmid-Fusion System training with Kendal Hirschi
	Childrens Nutritional Research Center · Baylor College of Medicine · Houston, TX

### **PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES**

C++, PYTHON, R, BASH, LATEX, HTML/CSS, OPENBUGS, MATHEMATICA